Guide to the Miguel A. Méndez papers S0964
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Miguel A. Méndez papers
1968-2009
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Méndez, Miguel A.
S0964
6.25 Linear Feet 5 boxes
Biographical / Historical
Miguel A. Méndez, was the Adelbert H. Sweet Professor of Law, Emeritus, and Stanford Law School’s first Latino professor. Méndez earned a BA from George Washington University in 1965, and a JD George Washington University Law School in 1968. Méndez, was a leading authority on both the federal and California rules of evidence, taught at Stanford Law School for more than three decades. Méndez died in 2017.
Scope and Contents
Collection includes teaching materials, correspondence, research files, as well as materials related to Méndez' involvment with campus Latino/a affairs.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 5 is restricted until 2084. Otherwise the materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Miguel A. Méndez, 2009.
Evidence (Law) -- California; Law -- Study and teaching (Clinical education); Méndez, Miguel A.; Méndez, Miguel A.; Stanford University. School of Law. Faculty; Stanford University. El Centro Chicano; MEChA de Stanford
- Papers, Accession ARCH_2009_220
  - Class evaluations - Evidence; Criminal Law; Trial Advocacy; and others, 1978-2002 (Box 1)
  - Faculty appointments, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Review - The Psych. Of Eyewitness Testimony, 1979 Sep (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Title VII Disparate Treatment Cases, Stanford Law Review, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Minority Alumni Dinner - correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - MECHA - correspondence and memoranda, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - La Raza newsletter, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - El Centro - memoranda, etc., 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bilingualism (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Lawyers, Linguists, Story-tellers, and Limited English Speaking Witnesses” (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hastings article, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hastings article, studies (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Teaching materials - correspondence, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Character evidence (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Minority admissions - correspondence, position paper, 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Stanford Bakke, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Michael Olivas - correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - EPA Clinic, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Stanford Chicano Alumni (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - State of California vs. Raul Ralph Flores - closing argument, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Congressional testimony [Méndez to Subcommittee on Employment Opportunities], 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chicano Law Students - correspondence, memoranda, newsletters, 1977-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lawyering process (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Curriculum Consortium, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - La Raza Amicus Brief, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chicano pre-laws, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Webb Ranch [Méndez’ letter to Campus Report], 1980s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Credit for clinical courses, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Concilio [de Asuntos Chicanos] - correspondence, memoranda, etc., 1982 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Tony’s [Amsterdam] clinical proposal, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Clinical application form (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Clinical programs: Stanford, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Clinical programs: other (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Southmost [College] speech, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Non-tenure review, memo on, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Intro - first year students (notes) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Annual faculty report [Méndez’ bio/bibliography information], 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Faculty evaluations of my teaching, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Personal (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters of recommendation [Méndez to sources for his own recommendation], 1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Early employment, 1968-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - MALDEF - correspondence, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - La Raza National Lawyers’ Association - correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Méndez statement on resignations (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - National Institute for Trial Advocacy - correspondence, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - SLS minority graduates (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Expressions of thanks, 2003-2009 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Law School efforts to hire a Latino, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Chicano faculty - correspondence, memoranda, etc., 1983-1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miguel Méndez - correspondence, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miguel Méndez - correspondence, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Miguel Méndez - correspondence, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Miguel Méndez - correspondence, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Méndez - Santa Clara, New Mexico (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Vermont Law School (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Cranston [Alan] - correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Bakke CRLA briefs, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Clinical applications, 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Lawyering process class (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Teaching Fellows, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Teaching Fellows, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Teaching Fellows, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Teaching Fellows Information, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Teaching Fellows Announcement, 19861987 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Restricted Materials
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials are restricted until 2084.
  - Federal Court (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Recommendations - students (Box 5, Folder 2)